<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before Their Majesties, K. William and Q. Mary's forces, at Gant in Flanders the Sunday before they marched into the camp, 1694 / by John Petter ... ; published at their request.</title>
            <author>Petter, John, 1661 or 2-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1890</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33393</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13291959</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13291959</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98844</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98844)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1039:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before Their Majesties, K. William and Q. Mary's forces, at Gant in Flanders the Sunday before they marched into the camp, 1694 / by John Petter ... ; published at their request.</title>
                  <author>Petter, John, 1661 or 2-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for Edw. Evets ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98844:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98844:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before Their Majeſties, K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary</hi>'s FORCES, AT <hi>GANT</hi> in <hi>FLANDERS,</hi> The <hi>Sunday</hi> before they marched into the <hi>Camp,</hi> 1694.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN PETTER,</hi> M. A. Chaplain to Her Majeſty's Regiment of Horſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Honourable Brigadier <hi>Lumley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd at their Requeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>Edw. Evets,</hi> at the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:98844:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Humph. Hody,</hi> Reverendiſſimo in Chriſto Patri ac Domino Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino <hi>Johanni</hi> Div. Provid. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiep. <hi>Cant.</hi> à Sacris Dom.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May 28. 1694.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98844:2"/>
            <head>To the Officers, and Soldiers of Their Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Engliſh Forces of the Garriſon of <hi>Gant</hi> in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAD I deſign'd to have publiſh'd this Sermon, or could I have foreſeen I ſhould have been requeſted to do it by you, it might have appear'd more correct, but you know my attendance on the Publick Service of the Church twice a Day, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the many other neceſſary Duties of ſo great a Garriſon, left me but a very little time to provide for this which came ſo quick about; the conſtant performance of it being made neceſſary oftentimes each Week by the many ſubtle Contrivances, and cunning Devices of the <hi>Romiſh Prieſts</hi> to corrupt and debauch your Principles of Religion, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance; and amongſt many others their great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence they employed this way to ſeduce you from your bounden Duties to God, and Their Majeſties; theſe, with the great ſincerity of my intentions of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my utmoſt to promote God's Glory, the good of the Church, and Their Majeſties intereſt among you,
<pb facs="tcp:98844:3"/>
I hope may apologize for thoſe Defects which ſhall be obvious to you in the reading, that might perhaps eſcape you in the hearing: Now God grant that theſe, with all my other well deſign'd, though mean Performances among you, may produce their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and much wiſh'd for Effects. Though the Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal that the extravagant Looſeneſs and Liberties of of ſome among you hath brought upon ſo honourable and noble a Profeſſion be very great, and much to be lamented; yet I muſt do you ſo much juſtice as to own to the World, that I have ever found among many of you, a great readineſs to encourage the meaneſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours tending to the Promotion of any of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd ends, <hi>viz.</hi> God's Glory, the good of the Church, and Their Majeſties intereſt; of which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many others, your earneſt Requeſts for the printing of this following Diſcourſe, are a ſufficient Inſtance, and my Compliance with them the greateſt I can give of my being what you ſhall find me on all Occaſions,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Gant, <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> the 30. <hi>N. S.</hi> 1694.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt obedient, and very humble Servant, <hi>John Petter.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98844:3"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 SAM. IV. part of verſ. 9.</bibl> —<hi>Quit your ſelves like men.</hi>—</q>
            </head>
            <p>GOD Almighty, when his people went out to battel, orders the Prieſt ſhould approach, and ſay unto them, <hi>Let not your hearts faint, fear not, and do not tremble, neither be ye terrified becauſe of them,</hi> Deut. 20. 2. and ſuch forms of ſpeech as this we find frequently uſed in Scripture at the opening of their Campagnes, or before they entred upon any Action, to excite and ſtir up, to animate and encourage both Officers and Soldiers, to behave themſelves manfully and with undaunted reſolution.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, the time of your marching now drawing near, and this being the laſt day of your meeting together in this place, I have in comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with ſo ancient and ſo good a cuſtom, cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to addreſs my ſelf to you in theſe words, <hi>Quit your ſelves like men:</hi> and in handling of them I ſhall doe theſe four things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Shew you what it is to <hi>Quit your ſelves like men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The beſt and ſureſt way to doe ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98844:4"/>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The great reaſons you have to doe it at this preſent Counjuncture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly</hi> and <hi>laſtly,</hi> make one Inference from the whole; and conclude with an Exhortation to you, and with my hearty Prayers to the God of all Power, to protect your Perſons, and bleſs your Arms with good ſucceſs this enſuing Campagne.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſhew, <hi>Firſt,</hi> What it is to <hi>Quit your ſelves like men; Eſtote viri,</hi> ſo 'tis uſually tranſlated; and both this, and the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word, in their ſeveral Languages, ſignifie not any mean, or ordinary perſon, but a Man of Worth and Valour; ſo ſays <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Abner,</hi> 1 Sam. 25. 16. <hi>Art not thou a man, a valiant man, a worthy perſon; there is none like thee.</hi> But the words import more, and are more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly rendred by others, <hi>Eſtote in viros,</hi> a known <hi>Hebraiſm,</hi> as, <hi>Ero tibi in Deum,</hi> I will be unto thee for a God, that is, truly and effectually, to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purpoſes; ſo here, be ye for Men, ſtand not for Cyphers; fill not up only the places of Officers and Soldiers, but be what you appear to be indeed. Now there are ſome that are the peculiar vertues of every rank and condition of Men, and thoſe in Soldiers are theſe three: 1. Courage: 2. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlineſs. 3. Fidelity.</p>
            <p>And to <hi>Quit your ſelves like men</hi> in this ſtation, is,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98844:4"/>
to perform all theſe Vertues that are peculiar to that rank in which you are placed: So that you muſt be courageous, orderly, and faithfull to your Truſt, to <hi>Quit your ſelves like men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> You muſt be courageous, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in theſe three things:</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> Suffering chearfully any Hardſhips.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> Receiving boldly the Aſſaults of your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3ly.</hi> Fighting bravely whenever you are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Gentlemen, you muſt ſuffer chearfully any Hardſhips. You muſt be willing, ſo often as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion requires it, to feed low, and lie hard, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure heat, and cold, hunger, thirſt, and nakedneſs, to ſubmit to any terms, to be fed and cloathed, and every thing as your General pleaſes; to the moſt diſtant place, or through the fouleſt ways, or in the ſharpeſt weather, you ought chearfully (if your Commander give the Word) to march; you ought not to be diſcouraged, or affrighted with theſe, or any other hardſhips; but contentedly to live (if occaſion requires it) upon any the leaſt thing, nay, on nothing ſometimes but a bare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and never to mutiny for want of preſent Pay. And thus you ought willingly and chearfully to undergo theſe glorious Toils and Fatigues of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98844:5"/>
War, to endure a hard March in the day, and ſleep upon a harder Pillow at night: You muſt be content to ſleep with the noiſe of Drums and Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets in your Ears, and to be awaken'd with Alarms, to run on upon Spears points, and charge at the mouths of Cannons whileſt they are roaring out deſtruction; and thus you muſt follow Victory through heat and cold, hunger and thirſt, ſweat and blood, and ſeize, and pluck it from the arms of theſe hazards and difficulties wherewith 'tis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed and ſurrounded; and this is to <hi>Quit your ſelves like men</hi> in this reſpect, if you are thus cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageous in bearing theſe hardſhips and difficulties of War. You muſt alſo <hi>Quit your ſelves like men</hi> by being courageous,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2ly.</hi> In receiving boldly the Aſſaults, and bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the impreſſions of your Enemies. You muſt not be daunted (let the difference in number be never ſo great) with the approach of them; but (like <hi>David</hi> towards <hi>Goliah</hi>) run half way to meet them, no touch of evil muſt make you ſhrink, no appearance of danger make you give ground; but you muſt receive and bear all with an invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible courage, and not like thoſe delicate Youths in the Hiſtory, who were no ſooner touched in their tender faces by their Enemies weapons, but they threw down their own, and ran away; nor
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98844:5"/>
like the Children of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> Pſal. 78. 9. who <hi>being harneſſed, and carrying Bows, turned their backs in the day of battel,</hi> but like that Order of Ancient Knights in <hi>France,</hi> a part of whoſe military Oath it was, that they ſhould never turn their Backs upon their Enemies. The <hi>Lacaedemonian</hi> women were wont to charge their Sons when they went out to battel, <hi>Ut, aut vivi cum armis in conſpectum earum venirent, aut mortui in armis referrentur,</hi> that they ſhould either return with their Arms, or die in them. Even the tender Mothers among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> would not lament their Sons that fell in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, but rejoiced when their Wounds were in their fore-parts, and not in their backs, and you (Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) in thus receiving the Aſſaults, and bearing the impreſſions of your Enemies, muſt <hi>quit your ſelves like Men</hi> in this reſpect too. You muſt far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>quit your ſelves like Men</hi> by ſhewing your Courage,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> In fighting bravely, when-ever you are commanded to it: You muſt be as ready to be active as paſſive, to give as to receive Blows; and out-face the King of Terrours, and charge through all his Horrours with an undaunted Reſolution; you muſt mock at Fear, like the warlike Horſe in <hi>Job,</hi> and ſtand at the Mouths of breaches in the midſt of Thunder and Lightning; you muſt laugh at
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98844:6"/>
the impotent Threatnings of Danger, and bravely defie it, to do its worſt. In theſe lies the Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Courage of a Soldier, in bearing Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, enduring Blows, and hewing down his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and all theſe are implied in <hi>quitting your ſelves like Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A ſecond thing implied in <hi>quitting your ſelves like Men,</hi> is to be orderly; you muſt walk orderly,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> In reſpect to your Lives and Manners, by abſtaining from thoſe many outragious and unjuſt Practices, from that looſe and diſſolute way of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, which have brought upon your Profeſſion (though in it ſelf moſt honourable) ſo great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, and occaſion'd it by ſo many to be evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoken of in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> You muſt walk orderly in reſpect to your Superiours, and always have a mighty regard to the Word of Command; you muſt keep your Ranks and Files; for if a Soldier forſakes his place, and breaks Diſcipline, he caſts his Diviſion, it may be the whole Company into confuſion, and makes an eaſier Entrance for the Enemy. <hi>Nihil magis in acie cuſtodiendum eſt, quàm ut omnes Milites ordinem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedendi ſervent, periculum enim ab hoſtibus ſemper gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſimum ſuſtinet diviſus, &amp; inordinatus exercitus:</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98844:6"/>
de re milit. <hi>Mannius Curius,</hi> when Conſul, was wont to ſay, <hi>Non opus eſt reipublico milite, qui pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere non poteſt.</hi> The Commonwealth had no need of that Soldier, who knew not how to obey Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. When the Holy Ghoſt would deſcribe an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that ſhould be invincible, and bear all before them, he ſays, that they ſhould <hi>march every one in his way, and none ſhould break their Ranks,</hi> Joel 2. 7. You Gentlemen are an Army, but you are onely ſo, while due Order and Diſcipline is maintained, and every Officer and Soldier keeps his own place and ſtation; but when theſe are neglected, and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled under foot, you are quite another thing, you may be a Multitude or Rout, but you will hardly bear the Name of an Army, without this Order, all things would run into preſent confuſion: 'Tis not in your choice to ſtand where you will, and do what you liſt in this Army, but you muſt every one of you faithfully diſcharge that Duty, and diligently manage that particular place which is committed to your Truſt; You muſt at all times with chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs obey the Orders of your Superiours. When you are commanded to march on, you muſt not (though the Danger be ne'er ſo great) endeavour to retreat, when to wheel to the right you muſt not (upon any conſiderations) endeavour to do it to the left. As one once complained, <hi>Ordo Militum
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98844:7"/>
nunc eſt ordinem non tenere,</hi> as if the Excellency of a Soldier conſiſted in contradicting and thwarting the Commands of his ſuperiour Officers; and this is the <hi>2d</hi> thing implied in <hi>quitting your ſelves like Men,</hi> to be orderly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> The <hi>3d</hi> thing implied in <hi>quitting your ſelves like Men,</hi> is to be faithfull to your Truſt (that is) not to betray it for any temptation of intereſt or advantage, nor to be ſo mercenary to engage on any ſide for pay, without regard to what is right, or wrong. This the <hi>Romans</hi> took ſuch care of, that they liſted none into their Service, but they obliged them to take an Oath to that purpoſe, which they call'd by the great and venerable Name of <hi>Sacramentum;</hi> a thing ſo ſolemn with them, that the Chriſtians have choſe to borrow that Word, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their entrance into Covenant with God by: we do at this Day follow their Example, and ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to obſerve your Oath, is to be faithfull to your Truſt; I think it therefore not amiſs to repeat it to you at this preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſwear to be true to our Sovereign Lord, and Lady, King</hi> William, <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>and to ſerve them honeſtly, and faithfully, in the Defence of their Perſons, Crown, and Dignity, againſt all their Enemies, and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers whatſoever; and to obſerve, and obey Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Orders, and the Orders of the Generals, and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98844:7"/>
ſet over me by Their Majeſties: So help me God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſufficiently inſiſted on the firſt thing which I propoſed, and ſhewn you what it is <hi>to quit your ſelves like Men,</hi> I proceed now to the ſecond, which is the beſt and ſureſt way to do ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> The beſt and ſureſt way to do ſo, is to be religious; to be couragious, orderly, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, is to <hi>quit your ſelves like Men;</hi> and theſe, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, are qualifications which you wiſh to be in all that are under your Command; becauſe without theſe the Service that the Publick, or your ſelves can expect, muſt be but very ſmall: It is not difficult to gueſs at the many ſad Conſequences of being at the Head of a Body of cowardly, diſorderly, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull Wretches; therefore if I can make it appear, that Religion will effect theſe three things, and make you, <hi>1ſt.</hi> More couragious, <hi>2dly.</hi> More orderly, <hi>3dly.</hi> More faithfull to your Truſt; I doubt not but 'twill abundantly convince you, that the beſt way to be good Soldiers, is to be good Men, and that the onely, and ſureſt way to <hi>quit your ſelves like Men,</hi> is to fear God, and keep his Commandments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt,</hi> Therefore I ſhall ſhew you, that being reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious will make you the more couragious, without which, ſuch Gentlemen as you are uſeleſs in the World: You heard in the beginning of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, that God Almighty when his People went
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98844:8"/>
out to Battel, ordered the Prieſt ſhould approach, and ſay to them, <hi>Let not your hearts faint, fear not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. 2. Now after that, the Officer was to ſay again to them, <hi>What Man is there that is fearfull, and faint-hearted? let him go, and return to his Houſe,</hi> verſ. 8. It is not to be denied but that ſome Men, who are very bad, are very ſtout, daily experience evinceth this; there is a ſort of Audacity, and Fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hardineſs, which is a reſemblance of true Valour, and which the worſt of Men are capable of, but this is a brutiſh ſort of Bravery, like the Valour of an Horſe, that runs into Battel without fear or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. But alas! ſuch an irrational Valour, which you owe merely to your conſtitution, will laſt no longer than your inconſideration: For when the <hi>impetus</hi> is once over, and you come ſoberly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate your preſent Affairs, and to take a true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of your future State, your Spirits will then flag, and your ſtoutneſs become as nothing. For who can imagine, that you will in cool Thoughts, with any Courage venture your Lives, when your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences tell you, you are in no meaſure prepared for Death? But he who hath well-grounded hopes of a better Life, how undauntedly, when he is lawfully call'd to it, will he hazard this? This is that to which the Apoſtle attributes the Heroick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances of thoſe religious Champions of old,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98844:8"/>
               <hi>Gideon, Baruch, Samſon, Jeptha, David,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. it was <hi>through faith they ſubdued Kingdoms, waxed valiant in fight, and put to flight the Armies of the Aliens.</hi> A firm belief in God will make a Man va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant in the midſt of the greateſt Dangers, but Vice and Irreligion makes men Sneaks, and Cowards, and a Wing of Miſcreants have juſt reaſon to flee, when Death is coming out of a Cannon's Mouth, the Muzzle of a Gun, or upon the Point of a Sword, becauſe the formidable Appearance of Hell is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too, and then the Hearts of irreligious Men will recoil, and evil Conſciences will be apt to make them run into Pits, or Woods, or into any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners on this ſide the Territories of the damned. Take this, Gentlemen, for a general Rule, that none ſhall undertake an Enterprize with ſo much Readineſs, or engage with ſo much Fortitude, or maintain his Ground with ſo much Conſtancy, or defie the roarings of the Field with ſuch a fix'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, as the Man who is girt about with Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, and to whom a good Conſcience is a Coat of Mail. For as a <hi>Pagan</hi> Philoſopher ſaid, <hi>He that loves God receives Death willingly, and is not cow'd at its Approaches, but keeps his Station, and his Poſt with a ſteel'd Courage;</hi> So that you ſee, this is one good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence Religion hath upon Gentlemen of your profeſſion, it makes them the more couragious.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98844:9"/>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> It will make them more orderly too. The diſſoluteneſs, and rudeneſs of Armies is ſo common and notorious, that they are often dreadfull to their own ſide, almoſt as much as to their Enemies. The ſharpeſt Puniſhments that were ever yet inflicted for any Crime have not been able to terrifie ſo, but that in ſuch a Body, there are ſtill many, who will venture to commit the ſame. But though all the Care, and Severity of Diſcipline is not able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Diſorder in any kind, yet this will. The good Man hath a Rule within him, more exact, and ſtrict than any martial Law, that whereas others by their violent Outrages, and domineering Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, enrage the People, and bring their Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into diſrepute, he will demean himſelf ſo, as to be able to make St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Appeal whereſoever he hath had his quarters; <hi>Ye are Witneſſes, and God alſo, how holily, and juſtly, and unblameably we behaved our ſelves among you.</hi> Whence come the wrongs, and waſtings, the ſwaggerings, and inſolencies, the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancies, and immoralities complained of in all Ages among the Soldiery? Come they not hence, even <hi>of your luſts that war in your Members,</hi> from the want of Religion, and the Fear of God? This would lay the Ax to the Root of ſuch flagitious Enormities, reſtrain your Paſſions, bridle your Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, and make you ſo ſober, ſo civil, and ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98844:9"/>
that your company would be as much deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in all places, as now (I am ſorry to ſay it) 'tis with too much reaſon dreaded: and this is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother good effect Religion has on a Soldier, it makes him more orderly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3ly.</hi> The third influence Religion hath upon a Soldier is, It will make him more faithfull to his truſt, which he is obliged to be (as you have heard) by the Oath he takes when he is firſt liſted. But what are Oaths, and where are the force of them, if men have no real ſenſe of Religion? like <hi>Samſon</hi>'s Withs, they may pretend to be bound with them, but when they think fit they will as eaſily ſnap them in ſunder. <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us of the Father of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> that once it came into his mind to give out, that all that ſerved him in any Office, ſhould ſacrifice to Idols, or elſe quit their places, when the time came that they had all given in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations; quite contrary to their expectations, thoſe that choſe rather to lay down their employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than to wound their conſciences, he kept in, or advanced to higher truſt, thoſe that to comply with his humour, and, as they thought, their own intereſt, were ready to turn Idolaters, he diſmiſſed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>For how</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhould I imagine, but that upon occaſion theſe men will be treacherous to me, that make no more of being ſo to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98844:10"/>
their God?</hi> But the fear of him is the beſt ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for any man's Fidelity, if it be ſo that he truly and indeed fears God, upon this account he will fear to be falſe to Men; and this is the third in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence Religion hath upon a Soldier, it makes him more faithfull to his truſt. So that ſince Religion will make you more courageous, orderly and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to your truſt, 'tis evident that to <hi>fear God, and keep his Commandments</hi> is the beſt and ſureſt way to <hi>quit your ſelves like men;</hi> which was the ſecond thing I propoſed to ſpeak to.</p>
            <p>Now, Gentlemen, before I ſpeak to the third thing, I ſhall beg your patience whileſt I make one Obſervation, and reflect a little upon your general and great neglect of this main point, hoping there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to bring Religion into greater eſteem among you, and to prevail with you, to be more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the future of this one thing neceſſary, it being (as you have heard) the ſureſt way to gain that noble Character (which is, or ought to be the deſire and ambition of you all) of <hi>quitting your ſelves like men.</hi> There is generally ſo much licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and wickedneſs among the Soldiery, that the Poet hath ſcandalized the whole Tribe upon that account, <hi>Nulla fides, pietaſque viris qui caſtra ſequuntur. Theſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are a ſort of people that have no manner of religion or honeſty at all in them.</hi> A
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98844:10"/>
great deal of pity it ſhould be ſo at any time; it is ſad, and may prove dangerous to have the Sword in ſuch mad Mens hands: But I think the Poet was much to blame, to condemn all for the ſake of ſome: For though it be ſo among too many, yet 'tis not ſo univerſally true, but (that God be thanked) there be ſome exceptions: and many (to your great honour, Gentlemen, be it ſpoken) that are employed in this preſent Service. Why ſhould Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be thought inconſiſtent with your Profeſſion? whatever liberties too many of it give themſelves, it has been as famous for Men eminently pious as any whatſoever: The firſt Man that we read pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſt after his Crucifixion was a Soldier; in that hour of darkneſs, when his Followers fled, his Diſciples fainted, and the Rabble derided him, a Soldier and his Company owned him; <hi>Matt. 27. 54. The Centurion, and they that were with him feared greatly, and ſaid, Truly this was the Son of God. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen</hi> in his time had a <hi>Caeſarius,</hi> Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> a <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius;</hi> and a Learned Writer, ſpeaking of the Noble Army of Martyrs, ſaith, <hi>Pars melior ex militibus,</hi> The greater part of them were Soldiers. The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter which S. <hi>Luke</hi> gives of <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, That <hi>he was a devout man, and one that feared God with all his houſe, which gave much alms to the people, and prayed to God alway,</hi> Acts 10. 2. I have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98844:11"/>
inſtanc'd in this laſt, as a Pattern worthy your imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and with a deſire that you would compare the practice of this noble <hi>Roman</hi> with that of many of our preſent Army, and ſee what you can find, that can at all patronize that impious liberty and prophaneſs that is by ſo many recommended as reputable and ingenious, and is every day ſo much exemplified to us in common practice, that one would think it were entailed upon your Prefeſſion. The Centurion here mentioned was a devout Man, and zealous for Religion, one who endeavoured to promote it, by keeping up (all ways poſſible) its ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reputation in the world: Many among our Centurions make a mock of it, ſaying in their heart, there is no God, they ſit down in the ſeat of the Scorner; and though they cannot argue, yet reſolve to laugh all Piety out of countenance. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the dulleſt Creature, that can but revile his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, make a prophane Paraphraſe upon the Holy Writ, vent an impious Jeſt, ridicule any thing that is Sacred, and ſtoutly diſclaim his Maker, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately proclaimed a Wit, not conſidering that this is direct Blaſphemy. 'Tis ſaid farther of this Centurion, <hi>that he feared God;</hi> they cannot in the leaſt pretend to this part of the Centurion's chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, who upon every impertinent occaſion, take his moſt ſacred Name into their prophane Mouths,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98844:11"/>
and call upon him to witneſs to every trifle, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to a lye. Sure, Gentlemen, you cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the <hi>fear of God,</hi> who call upon him almoſt every moment to damn your ſelves, your deareſt friends or acquaintance for every frivolous diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, nay often for nothing; whoſe mouths are full of bitterneſs and curſing, who challenge to your ſelves the liberty of your tongues, ſaying in the words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>We are they that ought to ſpeak, Who is Lord over us?</hi> Pſal. 12. 4. Nay, there are ſome among you (I think my ſelf obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in duty to take notice of it) who are ſo far from <hi>fearing God,</hi> that you ſeem to be perfectly of the temper of the unjuſt Judge mentioned in Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> who <hi>neither feared God, nor regarded man.</hi> If it were not ſo, though the <hi>fear of God</hi> could not reſtrain you, yet otherwiſe in reſpect of Men, you would ſometimes abſtain from all ſorts of impious, leud, prophane and atheiſtical diſcourſe, and at leaſt comply with the rules of civility, though you will not with thoſe of piety. For your unſavoury breath (ſuppoſing no God to be offended with it) you cannot but imagine to be nauſeous to all thoſe who believe there is one, to all thoſe who have any Zeal for their Faith, you cannot think any diſcourſe more intolerable, or more diſobliging. Thoſe who do acknowledge a divine Power, cannot be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98844:12"/>
with eaſe and ſatisfaction to ſit by, and hear God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ridiculed and blaſphemed; you cannot but think this to be a very unpleaſant entertainment for any who believe a Deity; more eſpecially for thoſe who are more than ordinarily concerned for his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. The next part of this Centurion's chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter is, That <hi>he was one that feared God with all his houſe.</hi> Now if we compare the practice of ſome among you with this part of his character, it will be but too viſible, that you come far ſhort of it. I need not deſcend to particulars, for they are too evident; the many Oaths and Curſes, with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of other unſavoury diſcourſe that doth flow, almoſt every minute, from the mouths of the meaneſt and leaſt ſervant that does attend the Camp, ſufficiently proclaim the neglect of you their Maſters; who too many of you, by your own example, and the countenance and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you give to the vicious courſes of thoſe about you, ſeem to have taken up a reſolution contrary to that of <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s, and in your hearts to ſay, <hi>As for me and my houſe, we will</hi> neither of us <hi>ſerve the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another thing that is added in commendation of this Centurion is, That he <hi>gave much alms to the people,</hi> his <hi>devotion</hi> and the <hi>fear of God</hi> are accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with Works of Charity. How backward are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98844:12"/>
many of you to relieve thoſe, who by the fate of War, or any other misfortunes, are reduced to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and want; he was of a tender and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate nature; you may ſee here the mildneſs and ſweetneſs of his temper, by his being kind and mercifull; fruits of the ſpirit highly requiſite to preſerve thoſe of your profeſſion from tranſgreſſions of a crying nature, which too many of you, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, make light of, violence, cruelty, waſting, plundering, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But he in whoſe heart God had put it, to give that which was his own to others, when their neceſſities required it, could not but abhor to take and detein that which was not his own from others; no, he walks according to the <hi>Baptiſt</hi>'s rule of <hi>doing violence to no man, and being content with his own wages.</hi> But inſtead of walking according to this example, and relieving to the utmoſt of your ablity the people, and aſſiſting thoſe that are under your command, how many of you take all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to ſqueez and oppreſs the former, and to doe all the injuſtice you are able to the latter; and, like miſcreant <hi>Achans,</hi> make it your buſineſs by theſe indirect ways to enrich your ſelves, not fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Curſe of God on ſuch ill-gotten treaſure?</p>
            <p>The laſt thing that is ſaid in praiſe of this Centurion is, That he <hi>prayed to God alway,</hi> that is, every day, at the ſet and appointed times, when
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98844:13"/>
he was not hindred by other lawfull occaſions. In an undertaking attended with ſo many and ſo great difficulties and dangers as yours is, he knew it would be impoſſible for him to ſucceed without imploring the divine aid and aſſiſtance; therefore he omitted no opportunity of repreſenting his needs, knowing that he might have them ſupplied only for asking. But how many among you, Gentlemen, rather chuſe to quit your hopes of protection and good ſucceſs in this world and happineſs in the next, than to buy it at the cheapeſt rate of humble Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? How many among you do neglect, diſuſe and contemn ſo eaſie a duty, the conſtant and due performance of which is attended with ſo many and ſo great bleſſings? What bleſſed opportunities are put into your hands? What an happineſs (by the pious care of our moſt religious and gracious King and Queen) do you enjoy, of having liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty (even in theſe Popiſh Countries) of addreſſing your ſelves to God in publick twice a day, in a moſt incomparable and a well adviſed form, and in a language underſtood by the meaneſt of the people? A bleſſing denyed to all that are round about you. And you, Gentlemen, who neglect to give your conſtant attendance on this duty, your circumſtances requiring it in a more eſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as I ſhewed you at large the laſt Lord's<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98844:13"/>
what do you but in effect declare to the World, that you look no higher than your ſelves, your own Strength and Valour, your own Skill and Conduct, and that you do repoſe all your confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the Arm of Fleſh, or that you think pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and good ſucceſs Bleſſings hardly worth your asking, or elſe with thoſe prophane Wretches in the Pſalmiſt, that <hi>you care not for God, neither is God in all your thoughts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Gentlemen, it may perhaps be thought by ſome among you, that theſe reproaches are too ſevere, but the Pulpit is to be pardoned plainneſs, becauſe the Grave deals roundly, and therefore I hope you will bear with them; eſpecially conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of what importance to the Publick ſuch a Body of Men as you are, who are of ſo great uſe in the World, that every Nation and People, have with one conſent juſtly accounted you worthy of all Eſteem and Honour; ſo that <hi>if the light that is in you ſhould be darkneſs,</hi> by reaſon of the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of it, how <hi>great might that darkneſs prove?</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh,</hi> diſcourſing whether the <hi>Greeks,</hi> or <hi>Romans,</hi> were the better Soldiers, very fairly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, <hi>that the Engliſh were better than both;</hi> nor is this the particular judgment of a Countryman of your own, but you have a general Renown in all the Nations that are round about you, and the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98844:14"/>
Character which he long ſince gave of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, hath by the opinion of the greateſt Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals the World ever bred, together with the many Noble exploits you have atchieved ſince in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of many Nations been ſufficiently confirmed; if to this, you would add that of the Centurion, to be devout Men, fearing God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then you would be perfect, and lacking nothing, and thereby free your profeſſion from that ill opinion which the great looſeneſs, and horrid prophaneneſs of ſome among you hath brought upon it; and thus removing theſe unhappy occaſions of your diſ-eſteem, all Nations round about you would record you for the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of the Earth, and you would abroad, as well as at home be thought worthy of double Honour; you would then be an Honour, as well as a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to your Country, Their Majeſties and the whole Kingdom would prize and eſteem you, and God would bleſs you, bleſs you with Honour, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and good Succeſs in this World; and when you have thus fought a good fight, and finiſhed your courſe, and kept the Faith, henoeforth there would be laid up for you a Crown of Righteouſneſs in the World to come; thus having ſo well grounded hopes of a better life, what can be a ſurer way to make you <hi>quit your ſelves like Men,</hi> than in expoſing this? (when there is ſo juſt an occaſion for it) which brings me to ſhew you,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98844:14"/>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The great reaſons you have to do it at this preſent Conjunction; which I don't doubt will appear to be very great, and I hope powerfull too, if you conſider theſe four things:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Excellency of that Government, thoſe Laws and Liberties you have to defend.</item>
               <item>2. The Church and Faith you contend for.</item>
               <item>3. The Defenders of the Faith you have to ſerve.</item>
               <item>4. The Enemy you are to oppoſe: Conſider, Gentlemen,</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> That Government, thoſe Laws and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties you have to defend; and you will find them ſuch, that if any where upon the Face of the Earth, you muſt confeſs, that there is the eaſie Yoak, and light Burthen: How ſecure do they render to you all your civil Rights? Your Liberties are ſuch, that while our Sovereign Lord and Lady ſit upon Their Throne in the brightneſs of Imperial Majeſty, the meaneſt Subject may as truly ſit under his Vine, and Fig-tree, and enjoy his own with ſecurity, peace and plenty: You your ſelves, Gentlemen, who have ſeen the ſad and dolefull Circumſtances of poor Peaſants in theſe Countries, know full well, that <hi>God hath not dealt ſo with other Nations:</hi> You may all of you gratefully ſing as the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:98844:15"/>
did, <hi>Pſal. 16. 6. The lines are fallen to us in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant places,</hi> and we have through the Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, a goodly Heritage: Yours is one of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Iſlands; the Government is of that rare bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and temperament, that you cannot but have a deep ſenſe of the many Bleſſings you all enjoy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it of thoſe wofull Miſeries and Diſtractions you were all expoſed to, by the Violences offer'd to it in the late Reign: This is well worthy your higheſt Valour, well worthy your trueſt Fidelity; all your welfare is apparently bound up in the welfare of this Government; and that Government that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves you, that it may ſo do, muſt be inviolably preſerv'd by you, and certainly 'tis a great debt, and duty which you all owe to it, 'tis yours, as well as Their Majeſties Safety; 'tis a concern ſo eſſential, that what the <hi>Roman</hi> Oratour ſays of Government, in general, may as truly be ſaid of that of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſties, <hi>That neither Family, or City, neither People, nor Country, could any longer ſubſiſt without it:</hi> He therefore that faithfully ſtands by it, ſhews him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Friend to his own, and Country's ſafety, as well as a true and faithfull Subject to Their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties; I do not doubt therefore, but that as good Chriſtians, and true Engliſhmen, you will put on a generous largeneſs of Spirit, and with your lives ſtand firmly by it, and whilſt 'tis highly priz'd by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98844:15"/>
all Strangers, that you of the ſame Nation will not contemn, neglect, or abuſe it, but <hi>quit your ſelves like Men,</hi> in maintaining, defending, and ſecuring of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> The ſecond conſideration to move you to <hi>quit your ſelves like Men,</hi> is the Church, and Faith you contend for: A Church that owns the venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Antiquities of purer Times, and rejects the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd Incroachments, and Corruptions of later Ages; many of which in theſe Countries are daily viſible to your Eyes, though of ſome they ſeem to me to be aſhamed, by their abſtaining from the Uſe of them, in thoſe Garriſons where the Proteſtants are quarter'd, during the time of their abode there: All the Doctrines of your Church are ancient, holy, juſt, and good, ſuch as were taught by our Saviour Himſelf, when here on Earth practiſed by his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, deliver'd from them to the primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and ſo derived down to you. They are all of them moſt agreeable to the higheſt reaſon, in their conſequences tending moſt directly, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of Piety, and true Morality, the peace of Societies, and the good of every particular Perſon; they are ſo clearly ſubſervient to all good Ends, that if your deſign by Religion be, (what it ought to be) nakedly to ſave your Souls, you may then in communion with the Church of <hi>England</hi> paſs ſurely and ſafely to Heaven: God hath not dealt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98844:16"/>
ſo with other Nations; neither have they ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable freedom in his ways: You ſee, Gentlemen, in what blind ignorance they here keep their Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by the forbidding them under the moſt ſevere Penalties the uſe of the Holy Bible, or the reading any Proteſtant Books, or conferring with any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon upon any point of Religion, or the doing any one thing that may tend by the opening of the Eyes of the Blind, to the diſcovery of theſe Cheats; which Commands if any of them ſhould chance to tranſgreſs, it muſt be inſerted into the Catalogue at their next confeſſion, and they, poor Souls, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can be abſolved, and re-admitted to their half communion muſt undergo what penance the Confeſſour ſhall think fit, who for ſuch heinous Crimes as theſe always enjoins to be more ſevere, than for Theft, Whoredom, or Murther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You ſee what intolerable Burthens they lay upon them, how many ridiculous and fooliſh Ceremonies, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and uncommanded Penances they enjoin them, and none of them tending in the leaſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit the Souls of the ignorant performers, but all of them inſignificant to any other ends and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, but that of maintaining the Power, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing the Wealth of their Church. The Church you contend for enjoins nothing but what tends to the promoting of true Piety, ſhe hath crowded in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98844:16"/>
among her Doctrins, no Pardons, nor Indulgences, no Pilgrimages to the ſhrines of pretended Saints, nor vain Oblations to enrich her Coffers; ſhe hath thruſt in no Invocation of Saints, nor Prayers for the Dead; no pompous Proceſſions nor ſacred Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques to fill the pockets of her Prieſts; ſhe hath ſqueez'd in no Infallibility, nor Probability, no Enthuſiaſtical pretences to immediate Revelation, nor pretended Miracles to impoſe upon her People: You ſee therefore, Gentlemen, how much 'tis your intereſt, as well as your duty, if you ſincerely love God and your own Souls, or have any real deſire of your own, or others welfare, faithfully to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to that Church you have the happineſs to be Members of, and to <hi>quit your ſelves like Men,</hi> by vigorouſly maintaining and defending it againſt all Oppoſers whatſoever, and this is the ſecond conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to move you to <hi>quit your ſelves like Men,</hi> the Church and Faith you contend for: Now I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>3d</hi> Conſideration, which is the Defenders of the Faith you have to ſerve, and they are a King and Queen, profeſſing the ſame Faith with your ſelves, and worſhipping God in the ſame manner: An happineſs, and bleſſing long wiſh'd for in our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and I pray God long to continue it to us. Beſides how tender are they of all your welfare,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98844:17"/>
how carefull of your Liberties and Properties! how great encouragement do they give to Piety, Sobriety, Juſtice, and Charity, and every thing that is praiſe-worthy, both by their Precept and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Can you wiſh for, can you conceive any Princes more gracious, than thoſe whom God hath ſet over you, and hitherto miraculouſly preſerv'd, for the publick good and benefit of your Kingdom? Their onely aim and ſtudy is to make you a great and an happy People; for the effecting of which, 'tis plain, they ſpare themſelves no pains, no care, nor trouble: For this end to how many great, and inexpreſſible Hardſhips and Dangers has His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty willingly, and chearfully expoſed His Sacred Perſon, and with the ſame willingneſs and chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, doth ſtill continue to expoſe it, both by Sea, and Land? He, like the Noble <hi>Caeſar,</hi> in all his Commands in the Field, was never heard to ſay, <hi>Ite milites, ſed: venite; not go, but follow me;</hi> as if he ſcorn'd in all his on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſets to be any thing elſe but ſtill a Leader: He has always taught you, Gentlemen, by that which is the ſtrongeſt Authority, his own forwardneſs and example, and he ſeems to be one that the ſupream God hath taken particular care of, by Death's coming often ſo very near him, yet paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him by, and ſhunning him when it hath ſwept away almoſt all about him. I need not tell you
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98844:17"/>
the many narrow Eſcapes he lately had, nor how often he hath been miraculouſly and particularly defended in the midſt of the greateſt Dangers; but beſides theſe open Dangers, how many ſecret Snares of Death, that have been villanouſly contrived, and cunningly laid for him, hath he eſcaped? Yet he ſtill goes on with his uſual chearfulneſs and bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, to expoſe himſelf to theſe open and ſecret Dangers, for the good and ſafety of your Church and Kingdom. What Honour and Succeſs may you not yet hope to gain, when ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men of Valour are headed and led on by ſo experienced and ſo brave a General? whoſe Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Safety is to you all an high Concern. He hath, Gentlemen, laid on you all the obligations you can wiſh or deſire to <hi>Quit your ſelves like men.</hi> Beſides, 'Tis your intereſt ſo to doe, for 'tis endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to preſerve the Ship wherein you are all embarqued. If you would ſtrengthen the houſe, you muſt not weaken him that <hi>bears up the pillars of it,</hi> Pſ. 75. 3. Your firmneſs and ſteadineſs to him is, at ſecond hand, but a kindneſs to the Breath of your own Noſtrils. Thus whileſt your Royal Maſter, by his great Courage and good Conduct, endeavours all he can here; and your Royal Miſtreſs, by her moſt prudent and diſcreet management of Affairs
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98844:18"/>
in <hi>England</hi> in his abſence, does her utmoſt to make you a great and an happy People: What can you, Gentlemen, doe leſs than to love and revere them, to obey them readily and chearfully, to think your ſelves only capable of being made great and happy by making them greater and happier? Every Soul of you to be ſubject to them, ſo as ſtrictly to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all their Orders and Commands for Love of them, more than for Fear of puniſhment, to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent from all manner of murmurings and mutinies, loud only in their Applauſes and Thanks to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God for the felicities of their Reign. On which account, happy we their Subjects, the moſt fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and happy People in all the World: And this is the third Conſideration to move you to <hi>Quit your ſelves like men,</hi> The moſt gracious King and Queen you ſerve.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt Conſideration to move you to <hi>Quit your ſelves like men</hi> in this preſent Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture is, The Enemy you do oppoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the King of <hi>France:</hi> All his methods and ways of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing do ſufficiently evidence to the World, that he makes the Maxims of the common Enemy of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom the Rule and Meaſure of all his Actions, and that abſolute Power at home, with univerſal Empire abroad is his aim as well as the <hi>Turk</hi>'s;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98844:18"/>
and ſeeing that by theſe principles (which 'tis plain he hath taken up) all the duties of Chriſtianity are laid in the dirt, it were difficult to determine, ſhould abſolute Conqueſt (which God forbid) attend his Arms, whether under <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Turk</hi> Chriſtendom would obtain the faireſt quarter. All that the <hi>Turks</hi> have done in Chriſtendom ſince the time of <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt to this day, they owe to the Allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>France</hi> with the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Court, and to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion which the <hi>French</hi> have given in their favour. This preſent King hath learnt from <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt the moſt unchriſtian methods of making League with the <hi>Turks,</hi> by calling in (to his eternal ſhame) their aſſiſtance, to carry on his revengefull and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious deſigns, to the hazard of all Chriſtendom. He, under a ſhew of aſſiſting weak Princes, hath taken occaſion to ſhare with them in their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities, and by theſe unjuſt means, has vaſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed his own power. He has obſerved no rule of juſtice in making War, nor had any regard to it in obſerving Peace, when made. The War in theſe Countries is a ſufficient confirmation of both. 1. That grand Treaty between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> called <hi>The Pyrenaean Treaty.</hi> 2. That of <hi>Aix-la-Chapelle,</hi> unto which all the Princes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom were invited, to take care of the common
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98844:19"/>
Security. 3. The Treaty at <hi>Breda.</hi> I have not time now to relate theſe at large, and how ill they have obſerved them; together with their Treaties with <hi>Holland.</hi> And 'twould be too tedious to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat all that may give you proof of their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will and faithfulneſs to your own Countrey, as well as to all other Nations that have had any dealings with them: But theſe you may ſee at your lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the Collection of Treaties made by them with all the Princes and Potentates of <hi>Europe.</hi> I ſhall only remark at preſent, that the firſt of theſe Treaties was made upon a moſt ſolemn occaſion, that of Marriage, confirmed by an Oath, with the moſt Sacred Myſteries of their Religion at the high Altar; and yet was ſo palpably broken (as you may ſee, if you will take but the pains to peruſe the Treaty) that 'tis not to be parallell'd by any inſtance or example in all the World beſides. He has been the common Enemy of every State, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the Peace of the Government every where, ſowing of Factions in all Princes Courts, in their Councils, their Armies, or among ſuch of their Subjects as were inclinable to be factious; or elſe he hath jumbled one Prince againſt another by turns: And more than all this, He, Gentlemen, hates you and your Religion: He has been often
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98844:19"/>
heard to ſpeak theſe words, <hi>That his Grandfather loved the Proteſtants, his Father feared them, and he himſelf hated them;</hi> which any one that conſiders the Ruins of their demoliſh'd Churches, and the hard and miſerable Conditions (too large to be here recited) under which they are and have been oppreſſed in every point in that Kingdom, will eaſily believe. And now, becauſe many of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Party, both by their words and actions, ſeem to wiſh well to his Proceedings, I think it not a miſs to remark here, how their Religion is like to fare if he gains his Point; and this they may eaſily gheſs, by his dealings with them in <hi>Catalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Alſatia,</hi> theſe and divers other <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Countries, where all of them exclaim againſt his arbitrary and unjuſt ways of proceeding; How do they know how far Reaſons of State may drive him? How can they tell what Alterations they may (as they have ever done) oblige him to make? It behoves the Popiſh-party therefore to look to it; they may (if they pleaſe) hope the beſt, but you, and all the reſt of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant-party in <hi>Germany</hi> and other parts, will be ſure to be equal Sufferers with thoſe of his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as faſt as he can reach you, and then he will deal with you as he hath done with them, in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98844:20"/>
Concerns of your Religion, as well as of your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates; the former will be ſure to go down, and your conſtant profeſſion of it eſteemed ſo great a crime, that you will be thought altogether unfit to be truſted any longer with the latter. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts too have juſt reaſon to believe that their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhall receive conſiderable Alterations, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in ſecular Advantages of Wealth and Power, and that they themſelves ſhall fare but very indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently in reſpect to their temporal Concerns too, if they but conſider his arbitrary way of proceeding in <hi>France</hi> and all his conquer'd Countries. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it concerns both Papiſt and Proteſtant to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture their diſtinct Power and Intereſt in one common bottom, and reſolution to oppoſe him, and to hinder the obſtinate purſuit of his Project of Univerſal Monarchy. 'Tis certainly the true Intereſt of all to oppoſe his Deſigns, ſince no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is like his. And ſince you have heard that the Faith of Treaties confirmed in the moſt ſolemn and ſacred manner, the Good of Religion, the Ties of Blood and Amity, cannot hold him; you may doubtleſs believe it a very good reaſon at this Juncture, to endeavour to ſecure your ſelves and all <hi>Europe</hi> from the ſad Effects of his moſt unjuſt Courſes, by <hi>Quitting your ſelves like men;</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:98844:20"/>
and this is one great reaſon you have to doe ſo, and the laſt which I propoſed to ſpeak to, <hi>viz.</hi> the Conſideration of the Enemy you are to oppoſe. Not one of theſe forementioned Conſiderations, but would afford matter enough to fill whole Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes; but conſidering I am confined to ſo ſhort a time, I could ſay no more, but only give you theſe <hi>Items;</hi> and hoping they may put you upon reflecting on many more Particulars, and be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to obtain the deſigned End, I ſhall proceed to the <hi>fourth</hi> and <hi>laſt</hi> thing, which is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To make one Inference from the whole, and to conclude with an Exhortation to you, and my hearty Prayers to the God of all Power, to protect your Perſons, and bleſs your Arms with good Succeſs this enſuing Compagne. You are Gentlemen in whom their Majeſties and their Kingdoms repoſe great Truſt and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and on whom your own whole Nation, as well as others, have at this time fix'd their Eyes, obſerving your Motions, which way you will lead others, whether to the Right or Left: Your Care therefore, Gentlemen, ought to be the greater in the prudent government of your ſelves both as to your words and actions, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98844:21"/>
you give not the leaſt encouragement to thoſe who are ready to take fire from any little ſpark. But whileſt the unjuſtly diſcontented and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably Factious are plotting againſt the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and forming Deſigns againſt their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt Sacred Perſons; It well becomes you, Gentlemen, in your ſtations, to ſhew greater Zeal than ordinary for both, by liking whatever their Majeſties may judge reaſonable for them to doe in their publick Affairs, by diſcouraging all thoſe who approve or diſapprove of things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they themſelves are pleaſed, or provided for, or as they are influenced by ſome male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented or factious Leaders, by diſallowing, diſapproving and diſcouraging of that licentious Liberty that ſome take of miſrepreſenting, argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and arbitrating the great Affairs of State, of cenſuring, arraigning and condemning what and whom they pleaſe, by diſcountenancing all petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Speeches or Diſcourſes that may cauſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents or Diviſions of Mind, which would much better become the mouths of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemies, than thoſe who profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be true Engliſh-men and faithfull Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the King and Queen's: And no doubt but all Diſcontents would then be laid aſide,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98844:21"/>
and Diviſions, and Factions, ſoon dwindle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to nothing, when others have a precedent ſo good and powerfull as yours to influence their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, when they behold you a conſtant inſtance of this Truth, that the poiſon of faction, and ſedition, cannot infect all ſorts of Men: You therefore, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, having ſuch Laws and Liberties to defend, ſuch a Church and Faith to contend for, ſuch a gracious King and Queen to ſerve, ſuch an Enemy to oppoſe, what can be a more Noble Cauſe wherein to employ your Arms? What Cauſe can be more worthy of your Swords? In what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture can you more juſtly, or with cruer praiſe, <hi>quit your ſelves like Men?</hi> And ſince the onely way to do ſo is to be Religious, what remains but that you abſtain from all thoſe Vices which ſo uſually attend the Camp, and perform all good and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Actions ſo often as you have occaſion, and opportunity; making the Precepts of your Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rule and ſtandard of all your Thoughts, Words and Actions; and thus perfecting Holineſs in the fear of God, if it be your hap to fall in the Day of Battel, you will not fail to be rais'd from that Bed of Honour, to a Crown of Glory, which will ſufficiently convince you that your labour has not been in vain in the Lord: Now may His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98844:22"/>
this Summer become the happy Inſtrument to recover the Rights of the oppreſſed States, and Princes, of ſetting Bounds to the French Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to preſerve our Nation againſt the threatned Dangers, and to redeem <hi>Europe</hi> from that Yoak which they are framing, and deviſing to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her Neck, and to reſtore to us all, a Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Chriſtian, and an honourable Peace; may he then thus laden with Honour, Victory, and good Succeſs return in ſafety to his own People, and there together with Her Majeſty enjoy the bleſſed Fruits of his own Labour, by poſſeſſing his Throne in peace for many, many Years; and may they never want ſuch Subjects as you are, of ſo much Skill and Courage, of ſuch Loyalty and Fidelity, to defend Their Royal Perſons, and Government, againſt fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Invaſions, and inteſtine Factions and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and may you, Gentlemen, all live to receive the juſt Rewards of thoſe many Hardſhips, and Hazards to which you have ſo freely, chearfully and bravely expos'd your ſelves for Their Majeſties, and their Kingdoms; and then, though the Terrour of your Arms may be neceſſary for the Defence of Their Majeſties, and the Security of your Country; yet may they never after this Campagne have any more occaſion to try your great Skill, and invinſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98844:22"/>
Courage; and I don't doubt, though you are all Men of War, yet as Chriſtians you are ſuch lovers of Peace, that you will heartily ſay, <hi>Amen</hi> to it: I ſhall therefore diſmiſs you with the Words of the Pſalmiſt; where-ever you go, what-ever Action you are commanded on, <hi>The Lord proſper you, and cover your heads in the day of battel.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I wiſh you all good Luck in the Name of the LORD.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
